<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  Janis Erdmanis  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://janiserdmanis.org </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  My portfolio website  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://janiserdmanis.org/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Julia type system and multiple dispatch  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://janiserdmanis.org/blog/julia-experience/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://janiserdmanis.org/blog/julia-experience/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  I used to be a Python advocate as having an interpreter, meaningful error messages, docstrings, and easy library installation made the scope of what I could build expand tremendously. But in 2015, the Cython, Numba or C interop story became unbearable for my MSc thesis project, and I made a plunge into Julia, and I never looked back. As saying says, you come to Julia for performance and stay there multiple dispatch, type system, REPL, Pkg and other neat things.  ]]>
  </description>  
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Janis Erdmanis</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Properties of magnetic fluid droplets created by induced phase separation  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://janiserdmanis.org/blog/research-mdrop/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://janiserdmanis.org/blog/research-mdrop/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  In my master&#39;s project, I investigated the behaviour of magnetic fluid droplets formed through induced phase separation under varying magnetic fields. When subjected to fast-rotating magnetic fields of different intensities, these droplets exhibit intricate shapes such as oblate, three-axial, and starfish. The project aimed to determine whether a simple magnetic drop model could explain this complex behaviour under strong magnetic fields, where equilibrium arises from the interplay between scalar surface tension and linear magnetic force.  ]]>
  </description>  
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Janis Erdmanis</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Transitioning from Org to Franklin  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://janiserdmanis.org/blog/org-franklin/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://janiserdmanis.org/blog/org-franklin/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Like many, I serve my website with GitHub Pages, greatly reducing the burden. I don&#39;t need to maintain a server, pay a subscription fee or update certificates every six months, and I can focus on the content. However, now and then, technologies change, and I started to look at my website as a burden to keep it updated and publish new blog posts.  ]]>
  </description>  
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Janis Erdmanis</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Julia on a PBS cluster  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://janiserdmanis.org/blog/julia-cluster/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://janiserdmanis.org/blog/julia-cluster/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  A time comes when computation is too expensive to run. If you are lucky, you can adjust the parameters of the numerical method or find a better one. If that is not the case, you are now looking at what the phrase parallel computing promises. Often the numerical tasks can be reduced to actor-model, meaning that there is a single master giving orders to the computing slaves. Most programming languages give many tools for these capabilities; however, the way and complexity can alienate us from using them. I believe this is another strength of Julia which shows us a better and more elegant way: this blog post.  ]]>
  </description>  
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Janis Erdmanis</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>