<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  Janis Erdmanis  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://janiserdmanis.org </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  My portfolio website  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://janiserdmanis.org/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Reflection on 2017  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://janiserdmanis.org/blog/reflection-2017/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://janiserdmanis.org/blog/reflection-2017/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  It was a stressful but successful year. I published my first paper, concluding my scientific activities in Latvia, and with determination and support from peers, I entered the PhD program at TU Delft. In a completely unfamiliar environment, where I am compelled to develop myself further, aligning with my commitment for the upcoming year as well. Much more grounded than what I have achieved in the past year :&#41;.  ]]>
  </description>  
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Janis Erdmanis</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  My first year in TU Delft  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://janiserdmanis.org/blog/reflection-2018/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://janiserdmanis.org/blog/reflection-2018/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  I remember that after the first month, I promised to make a blog post on my studies here every month. I admit I had different expectations, so being under constant change makes it hard to reflect on how I feel, perform, and what future I see. But now, when my first year had passed in the TU Delft, and I was required to submit my self-reflection for the Go/NoGo meeting, I made a conscious effort on where I stand. Over this time, I have had some unusual thoughts which might form an opinion and recipes posted on my webpage. But for now, about my part of TU Delft.  ]]>
  </description>  
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Janis Erdmanis</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Understanding quantum state of emitted electron  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://janiserdmanis.org/blog/research-wigner/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://janiserdmanis.org/blog/research-wigner/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  At a nanoscale at cold sub kelvin temperatures and large magnetic fields, an electron for a few centimetres flows like photons on optical fiber coherently. This enables envisioning an electron interferometer experiment on a solid state device; thus, a question on preparing an electron quantum state becomes important. In my BSc thesis project, I derived and, using Python, computed the resulting state of an electron emitted from an electric field veil lowering one of its barriers.  ]]>
  </description>  
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Janis Erdmanis</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Julia on a PBS cluster  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://janiserdmanis.org/blog/julia-cluster/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://janiserdmanis.org/blog/julia-cluster/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  A time comes when computation is too expensive to run. If you are lucky, you can adjust the parameters of the numerical method or find a better one. If that is not the case, you are now looking at what the phrase parallel computing promises. Often the numerical tasks can be reduced to actor-model, meaning that there is a single master giving orders to the computing slaves. Most programming languages give many tools for these capabilities; however, the way and complexity can alienate us from using them. I believe this is another strength of Julia which shows us a better and more elegant way: this blog post.  ]]>
  </description>  
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Janis Erdmanis</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>